[Music]
like if you look at the two-year-old you
got the no then you got this notion of
like
this set of words results in
changes in behavior sure and then this
set of words results in changes of
behavior
that i can predict then this set of
words results in changes behavior that i
can predict and control
now i am full-fledged adult
person actually is the word i'm a person
right exactly
so you got your two-year-old who is
ruthlessly
there's no like there's no pretense
she's like she just iterates through
combinations of words and so she finds
the one that pushes the button she's
looking to push
like okay cool thank you for not like
not deceiving me
into thinking that right other than they
are
right right well then you'll watch at
four
what will happen is she'll start uh
playing around with a line
right right theory of mine drops in
right and then this whole idea of well
wait a minute i can
i can make reality happen
i distinctly remember coming in my
four-year-old daughter you know we told
her don't eat the cookies and you can't
come in and they're all over her face
you know it's like so where'd the
cookies go i don't know
did you eat cookies no what are they
cooking you know
but what about that uh chocolate on your
face
oh okay dad you know now all of a sudden
it's like ah
now i can't just mold reality completely
to my world
so uh yeah the way in which kids lie and
the more they lie that's actually a
better sign overall because it shows
cognitive flexibility and creativity as
long as you shape them
right right because you you need to be
careful to recognize as you said there's
boundaries that you know i can't lie to
a tree
i definitely can't lie to a forest fire
forest fires don't care about the words
i say
and the problem of taking reality like
you loop it back you you internalize and
metabolize
too much of reality as being a human
phenomenon
so you don't actually get a felt sense
of the boundaries of lying which is
pretty funny
um and then you know i guess if i can if
i can take that and kind of loop it all
away from the from the bottom you say oh
yes and by the way
humanness is also a forest right the
the basis of the systems of
justification
are sitting on top of a more
natural systems of coordinated behavior
to use your language right
and if i if i lie so vigorously as to
disrupt the underlying basis
of communication of justification at all
then i've really done myself a
disservice because i am what is called
it's a good i mean this concept of
justification the way i use has lots of
different
flavors and meanings so but systems then
are network systems of legitimizing
is an art basically okay so
the word paradigm the propositional
networks of paradigms
would be systems of justification okay
so is an odd or or what is true
and what is good exactly right okay and
there's there's a holding
of some kind of uh sort of network i'm
almost seeing almost like a matrix
which of course is the high dimensional
network that allows a particular
i guess now utterance right because they
were in language space
utterance to be positioned in terms of
its
value of truth and its value of
good uh-huh yeah exactly i i i think i
may have mentioned that this was
this question exactly this question was
my
my thesis at harvard i worked on this
piece
so it's interesting as you're saying it
i'm actually like in the back of my mind
trying to dust off the ways that i
thought about it
whatever it was 20 years ago um nice we
are coordinated so it's this
you know i have a i have an argument
and my argument is a modulation of
three things one is as you say the the
embedding
the embedding of a series of utterances
in a system of justification which is
trying to create as much value as
possible i'm trying to make as
true and good or valuable
uh right argument prop set of
propositions as i can put forward
yep and then one is the groundiness of
it
right the degree to which the truth the
epistemological framework of our system
of justification
loops back right because there's always
a bit of a checksum on the truth side
whatever you do don't do that because a
lion's about to eat you
the lion over there dude oh my
argument just fell to pieces
uh and then the third so the third piece
is then of course there's the counter
arguments there's a whole lot
other modulations of clusters of
propositions that are
are balancing you know in weight and
there's a sensing of okay we've
our paradigm has found a a a way of
of weighing these things against each
other right
and then as we do that we come to a way
of saying okay
that that's the thing that has the most
value the most
truth and the most goodness to it and
therefore
exactly exactly and then it's
hierarchically and centrally networked
so some of the unbelievably core things
right that are central to the
justification
system uh peter limberg you know did
that culture
multi-polar culture work yeah and he
identified all the different paradigms
and he had a wonderful table
where they had the core belief and then
the core antithesis
so who are the good players what are the
core beliefs that we justify what is our
big threat
okay so that shows sort of this the
systemic
hierarchical structural nature about
what's
central what's proximal to the system in
other words
uh another way of looking at like a
james madison university we have a
mission
statement right so then everything is
going to then
stem out from this value vision
truth statement and then how does it fit
um and are
are you a part of this system of
justification in a particular way
[Music]
you